Guide to the Alan Barth Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alan Barth papers
1937-1981
MS 867
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5
(12 boxes)
Correspondence, articles, speeches, editorials, subject files, newspaper clippings, and a small amount of personal papers. Half the papers consist of editorials written for the Beaumont Journal (1937-1938), the Washington Post (1949-1977), and the Guild Reporter (1950-1951). Both the correspondence and writings reflect Barth's involvement during the McCarthy period. The issues of civil liberties and freedom of the press run through much of his correspondence with Malcolm Cowley, John Fisher, Felix Frankfurter, Henry Morgenthau, Jr., and Adlai Stevenson.
Barth, Alan
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alan Barth, 1975-1976, and Adrienne Barth, 1981.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence. II. Writings and Subject Files. III. Biographical and Personal Materials. IV. Editorials.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Alan Barth deal in general with his profession as a writer and lecturer and with the liberal causes he espoused. The social and political issues of the 1940s through the 1970s are highlighted, in particular McCarthyism, civil liberties, intellectual freedom, and gun control. Among the more important correspondents are both political figures and editors, including Malcolm Cowley, John Fischer, Felix Frankfurter, Henry Morgenthau, Jr., and Adlai Stevenson.
The collection contains correspondence, writings, printed matter, newspaper clippings, and other papers, all of which are arranged in two series: Correspondence & Personal Papers and Writings & Subject Files. Series I is made up of three sections: Select Correspondence, General Correspondence, and Personal Papers. Series II also contains three sections: Speeches and Articles, Subject Files, and Editorials.
These papers were donated to Yale University by Alan Barth in two gifts of 1975 and 1976, and by Adrienne Barth in 1981.
Biographical / Historical
Alan Barth (1906-1979): newspaper reporter for the Beaumont, Texas, Enterprise, 1936, and Journal, 1937-1938; correspondent in Washington, D.C., for the McClure Newspaper Syndicate, 1938-1941; beginning in 1941 worked as editorial assistant for the Treasury Secretary and the Office of War Information; author of numerous books and articles.
Beaumont Journal; Washington Post; Civil rights -- United States; Firearms -- Law and legislation; Journalism; Freedom of the press; Press; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1953; Journalists; Barth, Alan; Bittelman, Eva; Block, Herbert, 1909-2001; Cowley, Malcolm, 1898-1989; Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980; Fisher, John Stirling, 1907-; Fortas, Abe, 1910-1982; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965; Friendly, Alfred, Captain, 1911-1983; Graham, Philip L., 1915-1963; Hook, Sidney, 1902-1989; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957; Morgenthau, Henry, 1891-1967; Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965; American Civil Liberties Union; American Friends Service Committee; American Jewish Congress
- CORRESPONDENCE & PERSONAL PAPERS, 1939-1981; Series I; 1.75 linear feet (4 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Barth's correspondence has been divided into two parts, with the correspondence of notable individuals and organizations having been separated from the General Correspondence and filed as Select Correspondence. Each part is arranged alphabetically, then chronologically for each individual. A good deal of the correspondence consists of comments, many of them quite lengthy, on Barth's writings and speeches, as well as letters of congratulations on his awards. Many of the exchanges with organizations concern speaking engagements, participation in conferences, and matters of publishing. The correspondence with the Center for Information on America, Harper's Magazine, and Viking Press in particular documents the evolution of several books and articles by Barth through lengthy discussions and criticism from editors Malcolm Cowley and John Fischer, among others. Additional correspondence concerning Barth's writings is located in Series II, Writings & Subject Files, because letters found filed with manuscripts have not been removed. It is therefore possible to find letters about specific writings in both Series I and II.
  Among the more interesting runs of correspondence is that of Felix Frankfurter, then a justice of the Supreme Court. The first and fourth amendments and freedom of the press are the primary concerns of these letters, and the two men express their own points of view on this issue. The result is a dialogue which weighs the merits of freedom of the press against the individual's right to privacy.
  There is an equally interesting exchange of letters with Henry Morgenthau, Jr., in which Barth expresses his support for Morgenthau's actions as Secretary of the Treasury under Roosevelt. Several speeches which Barth helped Morgenthau write are also included, in particular Morgenthau's closing address at the Bretton Woods Conference of July 1944. Similarly, the correspondence between Barth and Adlai Stevenson also includes a draft of a proposed speech on civil liberties written for Stevenson by Barth.
  Other interesting correspondence includes a letter to Barth from Richard H. Wels. Wels was the attorney for Senator Margaret Chase Smith in her libel suit against the authors and publishers of U.S.A. Confidential, in which Senator Smith was referred to as being under the influence of left-wing writers and reporters. Barth was named by the authors of the book as one of these. Wels asked Barth to explain the "nature and extent" of his acquaintance with Senator Smith, which he does in his reply.
  A series of eight letters to and from Eva Bittelman is also of interest. Her husband, Alexander Bittelman, was a Communist convicted under the Smith Act and was serving a three year sentence in federal penitentiaries where he was not allowed to write his autobiography and had his Social Security checks impounded by prison authorities. Eva Bittelman wrote to Barth asking for help in these matters.
  In some cases the correspondence of notable individuals is of little interest. This is true of the Franklin Roosevelt correspondence, for instance, where the correspondence is limited to one letter answered by Roosevelt's secretary. Similarly, there is a letter from Barth to John Foster Dulles, then Secretary of State, inquiring about the removal of one of Barth's books from two USIA libraries. Although the letter was not answered by Dulles, the reply represents an official policy statement by the Department of State and is noteworthy in that respect.
  Personal Papers is composed of biographical and personal materials, the biographical materials consisting primarily of newspaper clippings about Barth, reviews of his books, and published comments on his books and speeches. The personal materials include a small number of items such as government personnel forms, a publisher's agreement, and check stubs.
  - Select Correspondence
    General note
    An asterisk indicates ten or more items.
    - Agronsky, Martin, 1948, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Civil Liberties Union (*), 1952-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Friends Service Committee (*), 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - American Jewish Congress (*), 1953-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Baruch, Bernard M., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bittelman, Eva (Mrs. Alexander), 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Black, Hugo, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Block, Herb
      General
      See: box 2, folder 47-48
    - Buscaglia, Rafael, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - California, University of, Berkeley (*), 1957-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Celler, Emanuel, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Center for Information on America (*), 1962-1965, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
    - Colorado, University of, Boulder (*), 1951-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Combs, J.M., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Commager, Henry Steele, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Cornell University: U.S. National Students' Association, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Cowley, Malcolm
      See: box 2, folder 38-45
    - Crossman, Richard, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Douglas, William O., 1952-1964 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Dulles, John Foster, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Elliston, H.B.
    - Estabrook, Robert H.
    - Fahy, Charles, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Fischer, John S.
      See: box 1, folders 19-21
    - Fortas, Abe, 1952, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Frankfurter, Felix (*), 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Friendly, Alfred
    - Fulbright, J.W., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Graham, Philip
    - Harper's Magazine (*), 1952-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
    - Hook, Sidney, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Hoover, J. Edgar, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Jackson, Henry M., 1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Katzenbach, Edward L., Jr.
      See: Brandeis University, box 2, folder 57
    - Kissinger, Henry A.
      See: Confluence: An International Forum, box 2 folder 61
    - McGuire, Matthew F., 1939 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Mansfield, Mike, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Montana, University of, Helena, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Morgenthau, Henry, Jr. (*), 1944-1946, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Mount Holyoke College (*), 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Munoz-Marin, Luis, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - The Nation (*), 1951-1958 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Nebraska, University of, Lincoln (*), 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Ohio Civil Liberties Union (*), 1956,1961 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Playboy Magazine (*), 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      See also: National Issues Committee, box 3, folder 84
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1940 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Rostow, Eugene, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - St. Louis Civil Liberties Committee (*), 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Schlesinger, Arthur M. (*), 1949-1959 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Stanton, Frank, 1945-1957 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Stern, Isaac, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Stevenson, Adlai E. (*), 1952-1958 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Stone, I.F., undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Sweet Briar College (*), 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Viking Press (*), 1949-1966 (Box 2, Folder 38-45)
    - Waldrop, A. Gayle
      See: box 1, folder 12
    - Warren, Earl, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Washington Post (*), 1943-1959 (Box 2, Folder 47-48)
    - Wellesley College (*), 1952-1960 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Wels, Richard H., 1952 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Wisconsin, University of, Madison, 1953-1961 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Wiggins, Russell
    - Yale University Law School (*), 1953-1958 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Youngdahl, Luther W., 1959 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - General Correspondence
    - Ab - American College (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - American Council - Americans (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Amh - At (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Ba - Ber (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Bet - Bri (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Bro - By (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Ca - Ci (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Cl - Cond (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Conf - Cu (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Da - Di (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Do - Dy (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - E (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Fa - Fra (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Fre - Fu (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Ga - Gers (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Gerv - Gor (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Got - Gr (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Haa - Har (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Hat - Hi (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Ho - Hy (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - I (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - J (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Ka - Ki (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Kl - Ku (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - La - Li (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Lo - Ly (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Maa - Man (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Mar - Mes (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Met - Mil (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Min - Mot (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Mu - My (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Na - Neu (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - New - Ny (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - O (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Pa - Pe (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Ph - Pu (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Q (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Ra - Rob (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Roe - Ru (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Sa - Se (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Sh - Sl (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Sm - Ster (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Stet - Sy (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Ta - To (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Tr - Tw (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - U - V (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Wah - Wash (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Wass - Westl (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Westm - Wil (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Win - Wy (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Y - Z (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Unidentified (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Personal Papers
    - Legal papers, 1941, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Printed matter, 1944, 1950-1952, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Newspaper clippings re: Alan Barth, 1951-1953 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Checkstubs from the American Newspaper Guild, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 108)
- WRITINGS & SUBJECT FILES, 1937-1977; Series II; 3.75 linear feet (9 boxes)
  Speeches and Articles, arranged chronologically, consists of writings and addresses by Barth for a variety of publishers and other organizations, but not including editorials written for the Washington Post, the Beaumont Journal, and the Guild Reporter, which are to be found in section three, Editorials. Filed with many of the articles and speeches are related papers, including correspondence, newspaper clippings and printed matter, and other miscellaneous items.
  Subject Files consists of several folders of subject materials which Barth used in preparing his numerous editorials on gun control.
  Editorials is by far the largest section of the papers and consists entirely of editorials written for the Beaumont Journal (1937-1938), the Washington Post (1949-1977), and the Guild Reporter (1950-1951). The editorials are arranged in chronological order and present a compact history of the political and social issues of four decades. The emphasis of the editorials is on civil liberties in general and more specifically on several important issues including gun control, McCarthyism, freedom of the press and the rights of the individual, and immigration. A chronological list of the Journal and Post editorials for 1937-1968 is located in the register file.
  - Speeches & Articles
    - The Loyalty of Free Men (Viking Press); with correspondence and other papers, 1949-1953 (Box 4, Folder 109-113)
    - "McCarran's Monopoly" ( The Reporter ); with correspondence, 1951 May - August (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - "The Age of Doubt" ( The Progressive ); with correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Response to an article by Irving Kristol in Commentary; with correspondence, 1952 March - July (Box 4, Folder 116)
    - "A Moral Challenge to the Press" (address to the College of Journalism, University of Colorado); with correspondence, 1952 May - October (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - "Universities and Political Authority" (address to the American Association of University Professors annual meeting), 1953 March 27 (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Government by Investigation (Viking Press); with correspondence and other papers, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - "How Good is an FBI Report?" ( Harper's Magazine ); with correspondence and printed matter, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 120-121)
    - William Alanson White Institute address, 1955 January 29 (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Harvard Law School Forum address; with newspaper clippings, 1955 March (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - "Common Sense and National Security" (address to the St. Louis Civil Liberties Committee); with newspaper clippings, 1956 February 5 (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - "Intellectual Freedom and National Security" (Ohio Intellectual Freedom Conference); with newspaper clippings, 1956 April (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Cleveland Civil Liberties Union Address, 1956 December 7 (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Cincinnati Civil Liberties Union address; with newspaper clippings, 1961 January (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - "Public Safety and Private Rights" (Hoagland Memorial Lecture, First Unitarian Church, Omaha, Nebraska); with correspondence, 1961 July - November (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - "Report on the 'Rampageous Right'" ( The New York Times ); with printed matter, 1961 August - November (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - "The Press as Censor of the Government" (address at Marquette University); with correspondence and newspaper clippings, 1961-1964 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - Heritage of Liberty (McGraw-Hill); with correspondence, 1963-1965 (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Oliver Wendell Holmes Bill of Rights Award acceptance address, 1964 May 6 (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - "We Need a Firearms Control Law - Now!" ( Reader's Digest ); with correspondence, 1966 December - 1967 (Box 5, Folder 133)
    - "The New Migrants" (address to the Yale Law School Association annual banquet); with newspaper clippings, 1967 May 31 (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - "Taking Stock of Ourselves - The 1970 Census,", [pre-1970 Apr] (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Book reviews, 1970 March 3, undated (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - "Reduce Crime by Making Pistols Illegal" ( The Vancouver Sun ), 1971 December 9 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - "Courses by Newspaper: Free Speech, Assembly" ( Baltimore Evening Sun ), 1975 October 27 (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - "Earl Warren", undated (Box 5, Folder 139)
  - Subject Files
    - Gun control materials, 1940-1959, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 140-142)
    - Gun legislation materials, 1965-1970 (Box 5, Folder 143-144)
  - Editorials
    - 1937-1938 (Box 6, Folder 145-146)
    - 1949-1951 (Box 6, Folder 147-177)
    - 1952-1954 (Box 7, Folder 178-213)
    - 1955-1958 (Box 8, Folder 214-254)
    - 1959-1962 (Box 9, Folder 255-297)
    - 1963-1965 (Box 10, Folder 298-333)
    - 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 334-369)
    - 1969-1972 (Box 12, Folder 370-410)
    - 1974-1977 (Box 12, Folder 411)
    - undated (Box 12, Folder 412)